The county offered the same one hundred
and four acres three times. Three times
the courthouse steps went quiet when the
auctioneer asked for an opening bid. At
the fourth sale, in March, a
thirty-eight-year-old widow named Corinne
Ashbury raised her card and said
ninety-one thousand four hundred dollars.
It was very close to every cent her
husband's life insurance had ever paid
her.
For twenty-two years the kudzu had been
taking that place the way still water
takes a low field. First the fence line.
Then the hay barn. Then the shape of the
hills, until the whole property read from
the highway as one long green wave that
changed color with the season and never
changed shape.
Somebody near the back laughed, and then
two more. Every man on those steps had
fought the vines on his own ground and
knew how that story ended. What was out
there had stopped being a weed problem a
long time ago. It had become a landscape.
Not one person in that room knew that
under the vines, nine trees were still
alive. Neither did the woman who had just
paid for them.
Three weeks later she walked eighty-three
goats down the slope.
In Luke, chapter thirteen, the Lord
Himself told about a tree that had borne
nothing for three years, and about the
man who asked for one more season before
it came down. *Let it alone this year
also, till I shall dig about it, and dung
it.*.
Corinne Ashbury had three growing
seasons. Would that be enough?
Georgia tax sales happen on the first
Tuesday of the month, on the courthouse
steps. That Tuesday in March the wind
came down the street in front of the
Gilmer County courthouse cold enough that
the auctioneer read the parcel
description with his collar up, and the
men standing there kept their hands in
their pockets, which is its own kind of
bidding. They all knew it. They called it
the kudzu place.
Corinne Ashbury had spent twelve years as
a claims adjuster in Atlanta. Her job was
to stand in other people's driveways
after the worst week of their lives and
write down a number for what they had
lost. Three years a widow. She wrote
everything down and did not talk much,
and people often mistook the second thing
for the first.
Nolan Ashbury had been her husband for
eleven years. He died on a January
morning, his heart, before the ambulance
got up their street, and that is the
whole of it, because she never told it
longer than that to anybody. What he left
behind was a boy and a check.
The boy was Otis, eight years old,
waiting out of the wind in the courthouse
hallway with a pencil box flat on his
knees, counting ceiling tiles. He counted
things the way other children hummed.
The parcel was one hundred and four acres
east of the county line, with no
productive use in the record. Somebody a
generation ago had planted kudzu on the
road bank to hold the soil, which is what
people were told to do once, and the
vines did exactly what they were asked
and then kept going. Twenty-two years.
When the auctioneer asked for an opening
bid the fourth time, she said the number
without raising her voice, and the gavel
came down on ninety-one thousand four
hundred dollars.
She did not buy it to farm it. She had
driven past that wall of vines every
month for two years on her way to a
claims office in Ellijay, and a thing
valued at nothing had begun to look like
a thing nobody had looked at. That is not
agriculture. That is a woman who priced
losses for a living, buying the largest
one in the county.
What she had, besides the deed, was a
legal pad out of the claims office with a
column of figures down one side and the
word goats written across the top and
underlined twice. Goats eat kudzu. Goats
prefer it.
There was a condition, and she understood
it before signing. The land came in under
a conservation use covenant, which lets
working ground be taxed as working
ground. To keep it she had to show real
agricultural use, and a county appraiser
would walk the kudzu himself in the
spring of the fourth year. Three growing
seasons. If the covenant broke, the back
taxes and the penalty came due at once,
and no version of her arithmetic survived
that.
After the ninety-one thousand four
hundred dollars, after the fees and the
transfer, what was left would buy a used
stock trailer, a pair of school shoes in
September, and something under half the
goats on the legal pad.
She signed her name, took the key to a
gate nobody had opened in twenty-two
years, and drove out toward the only
thing the highway would show her, which
was a single color.
If you have ever been told that the thing
you wanted to save was not worth saving,
then you already know exactly how she
felt sitting in that truck with the
engine off.
The first walk in got her four hundred
yards in an afternoon. The vines had gone
over the fence and made a wall of it, so
she went in where a deer went in, on her
hands and knees, Otis behind her. Under
the leaves it was cool and dim, a green
ceiling twenty feet up in places, holding
the light out. The air smelled of wet
leaf and rot and, once, of something dry
and sweet, the way a pecan husk smells
after rain.
She found the hay barn by walking into
it. Otis found eleven fence posts and
reported the number.
From the crown of the slope the whole of
it showed at once, and that was the
problem. One hundred and four acres of
kudzu reads as a single object, and there
is nowhere on a single object to start.
Burl Tannehill was seventy-one, had run
goats on that ridge since his grandfather
ran them, and was the only man in the
county who did not laugh. He told her
what goats do, which is browse, up and
out, leaf and vine and bark, and what
goats do not do, which is anything a
person counts on. He sold her
eighty-three head at a price fair to both
and generous to neither.
He also handed her a brass bell on a worn
strap and said to hang it on the lead
doe. The doe was Pepper, gray-muzzled,
who came off his trailer like she owned
it, and the herd followed. In fog, Burl
said, the eyes are no good to anybody.
The ears still work.
They set electric netting and split the
near slope into paddocks of four acres.
Eight to ten goats to the acre, he said,
and move them before they get bored.
The last week of March she opened the
gate and eighty-three goats went down
into the vines. The sound was not what
she expected. Steady, dry, enormous,
hundreds of leaves at once, and somewhere
inside it, moving, the bell.
Merle Yates farmed the two hundred acres
along her west line, fifty-six, loud, not
a cruel man. He believed what he had
seen, and what he had seen was kudzu
outlast a bush hog, a dozer, and two
chemical companies. He stopped his truck
at her gate and watched the goats a
while. "Which one runs out first," he
asked. "That kudzu, or your money.".
In mid April she walked a paddock the
herd had stripped bare eleven days
before. The ground had been open. She had
seen the dirt. Coming up through it now,
in even rows down the face of the hill,
were new shoots, ankle high.
The kudzu had not been killed. It had
been mowed. Under every stem the root
crown sat in the ground like a closed
fist, twenty-two years of stored sugar,
and the herd had taken only the top. Two
seasons, Burl said on the phone. Maybe
three. Graze it, let it come, graze it
again, until the root spends what it
saved.
The other thing happened the same week.
There was an old hand-dug well below the
barn, on no plat, and the vines had grown
a lid across its mouth that looked
exactly like ground. One of the yearlings
went through. They worked past dark with
rope and a light, and Burl came, and it
was not enough, and near midnight he put
his hand flat on the winch and said her
name once, quietly. They filled the well
the next morning with rock and clay.
That night she sat at the kitchen table
with the ledger from her old work, the
one built for writing down what a loss
was worth, and this time she did not know
what to put in the right-hand column.
By the last week of October the east
slope had been eaten down to the shape of
the land under it.
The goats had worked that hillside in
rotation since August, four paddocks,
moved every nine days, and what they left
behind looked less like pasture than like
a room stripped of its wallpaper. Corinne
walked it on a Tuesday morning with frost
still holding in the low spots. Dead
vines hung off the fence wire in dry gray
ropes. And standing up out of the chewed
ground, straight, pale, wider around than
she could reach, were trunks.
She had walked past them all summer.
Under the green ceiling they had been
shapes in a wall of leaves, no different
from the old cattle chute, no different
from the well the vines had covered until
a goat found it.
She counted them twice, the second time
with her hand on each one.
Nine.
Burl came up the slope that afternoon,
put his palm flat on the bark, and said
the word before she could ask for it.
Pecan. Not young ones, either. He stepped
off the distance between the first two,
forty feet, then the next two, forty feet
again, and the grid ran on into the vines
where the clearing stopped. Somebody had
planted an orchard on this hill and
walked away from it, and the trees had
gone on standing in the dark for
twenty-two years the way a pecan will,
because a pecan can live past a hundred
years and has no interest in the plans of
whoever put it there.
The wind came up the slope smelling of
husks. That sharp green-shell smell. The
goats had left the split pecan hulls
where they lay.
Then Burl crouched down.
Around the base of the nearest tree, at
about the height of a goat's shoulder,
the bark was gone. Not scraped. Taken, in
a clean band all the way around, down to
pale wet wood.
A tree feeds itself through a thin living
layer just under its bark. Cut that band
the whole way around and nothing travels
between the leaves and the roots anymore.
The tree stands through the winter
looking like a tree. It will even leaf
out one more spring on what it has
stored, and then it dies with its
branches full.
Three of the nine were ringed most of the
way around. One was ringed all the way.
"They can't tell," Burl said. "A goat
don't know the difference between what
you turned her out here to eat and what
you'd give anything to keep. It's all
bark to her.".
Fixing it cost her twice. Welded wire
cylinders around all nine trunks, staked
deep, tall enough that a doe up on her
hind legs could not reach over the top,
and that was money already promised to
winter hay. The exclusion fence around
the grove pulled four acres out of the
rotation, and they were the four acres
the herd had been clearing fastest. Every
day the goats spent somewhere else was a
day the kudzu on that slope got back on
its feet.
She built it anyway, through November,
mostly in the rain, with Otis handing up
the staples one at a time.
He named the biggest one Big Tuesday,
because Tuesday was the day they found
it. He was nine years old that fall, and
that was reason enough.
Those nine trees had not given her a
single nut. What they had given her was a
reason not to sell the place that winter.
Ground like that — written off, grown
over, offered three times to nobody —
sits in nearly every county in this
country, and whatever is standing under
it has been standing there a while. Tell
us where you are watching from. Put your
town in the comments.
Dr. Nadine Croft drove out the second
Thursday in January with a soil probe
rattling in the bed of her truck.
She was the county extension agent, in
her forties, raised on a dairy farm one
county east, and her work was telling
farmers the truth about their dirt
whether they wanted it or not. Corinne
had called in October and again in
November and gotten nowhere, until she
stopped asking for an opinion and asked
for a test she would pay for. Letterhead
was the only language the courthouse had
ever spoken.
They pulled cores all morning. Fifteen
from the paddocks the goats had grazed
twice, fifteen from a strip along the
north fence still shut in under the green
ceiling.
The soil report came the first week of
February.
Organic matter in the grazed paddock ran
three point one percent. In the untouched
strip, two point four. Nitrate nitrogen
came back at twenty-six parts per million
against eighteen. Eighty-two goats
crossing a hillside all summer had put
more back into that soil than she could
have hauled in on a truck.
That part she had hoped for.
Nadine turned the page over, set her
finger on the control column, and said
that was the number worth looking at. For
soil that had seen no plow, no cattle,
and no fertilizer since before Corinne
was married, the nitrogen had no business
being that high.
Kudzu is a legume. Same family as beans
and field peas. Down on its roots it
carries nodules of bacteria that pull
nitrogen out of the air and fix it into
the ground, and the kudzu had been doing
that across one hundred and four acres,
every season, without stopping.
Twenty-two years.
The thing that had made the land
worthless had been feeding it the whole
time.
Corinne started a proper ledger that
winter — dates, paddock numbers, days
grazed, what the goats would not eat.
Twelve years of pricing other people's
losses had left her good at exactly one
thing, and now the thing being measured
was hers.
The money went out and none came in. Six
hundred dollars of hay in December. A vet
call at two in the morning for a doe with
pneumonia. Mineral, diesel, wire, a fence
charger after lightning found the old
one. Otis had learned to count to
eighty-two, and then backward from it,
and did it out loud at the gate every
evening. He had learned that number the
week they filled the well, and he never
once counted to the other one.
In the shed one afternoon, looking for
fence pliers, she moved a tarp and found
Nolan's toolbox. Green, dented, his
handwriting on a strip of tape across the
lid. The sockets still lay in the order
he had left them. She shut the lid, set
it back on the shelf, and finished the
fence with the pliers she had.
Burl came by at the end of the month with
a sack of mineral he said he had bought
by mistake. Under his arm was a Bible,
black, the cover gone soft as cloth. It
had been his wife's. He put it on the
kitchen table, opened it to a page she
had marked in pencil years before, and
left it lying open while he talked about
the price of hay.
I will restore to you the years that the
locust hath eaten.
He took the empty feed sack with him when
he went.
The county would come walk this ground in
the spring after next and write it down
as a working farm or as nothing. Two
growing seasons. That was all she had
bought.
By February the only thing on the place
that had not run out was the vines. And
the thing running out faster than her
money was the seasons.
The sound came up the ridge before the
light did. In the last week of June, in
the second summer, Corinne stood at the
top of the east cut and listened to the
herd eat.
A whole herd working a hillside of kudzu
made something closer to rain on a roof
two fields over. Where the leaf lay thick
the tearing ran together; where the slope
was opening it came apart.
That summer was the third pass over the
east cut and the fourth over the barn
slope. The first grazing takes the leaf.
The second takes what the plant shoves up
to replace it. The third and fourth take
what it cannot spare, because every new
canopy is paid out of sugar stored
underground, and that pocket is only so
deep.
By August the kudzu came back late, thin,
and low, and on the barn slope it never
closed over the fence line. Burl set his
boot on red dirt that had not been in
daylight for twenty-two years. He called
it the retreat, and told her not to call
it anything stronger.
The electric cooperative had eleven acres
of right-of-way gone to kudzu and briar,
too steep for a bush hog and too close to
live wire for a spray crew. Six hundred
dollars an acre, the goats hauled and
watered at her expense. Six thousand six
hundred dollars, and the animals ate the
invoice.
In September a burial association south
of Ellijay paid seven hundred and fifty
dollars an acre for four acres of
headstones. In October the school board
paid two thousand two hundred for the
bank behind the elementary ball field,
and let the third grade out to watch the
goats work.
Merle Yates had driven past that fence
for two seasons without stopping. That
September he pulled onto the shoulder and
got out.
"I laughed at you," he said. "Every man
at the feed store laughed, and I was the
loudest, and it wasn't meanness. I
watched two men take that ground. One
bush-hogged it a summer and quit. One
borrowed against his home place, sprayed
two seasons, and watched it come back
thicker the third spring. A man who's
seen two people go under doesn't clap for
the third one wading in.".
Then he asked what she charged by the
acre for the goats, and wrote it on the
back of a feed receipt.
The fog came the second week of
September. She went up at dawn to move
the netting and found the paddock empty,
the gate shouldered open, white in every
direction. She called, and the fog handed
her voice back flat. So she quit calling
and stood still. Below her and off to the
left, farther down than she would have
guessed, the bell. She walked toward the
bell the way a person walks toward a
porch light, and found Pepper in a stand
of sumac with the goats bedded around
her.
Driving home from the school job, Otis,
ten that fall, asked what she was putting
on the bill.
"Brush removal," she said.
He thought about it for most of a mile.
"That's not right," he said. "We're not
taking anything off it. We're just giving
it back.".
That night she opened the ledger from the
old job, the one she had filled for
twelve years with other people's losses.
For the first time since the auction, the
number in the right-hand column had no
minus in front of it.
Most of what gets sold as progress is
somebody in a hurry. That hill came down
because a woman refused to hurry, one
pass at a time, while a county waited for
her to quit. There is a kind of person
who hears go faster and slows down on
purpose. This channel is built for them —
subscribe, and stay with this one.
By April of the third year the east cut
was open enough to plant, and she planted
one strip, forty feet wide and a quarter
mile long — what she could water and pay
for.
Thirty-eight young pecan trees went in by
hand, Otis dropping a flag at every
stake. She did not buy an orchard. She
bought a strip, set it against the fence
of the nine old trees, and told herself
the next slope would come next spring if
the herd earned it.
Nadine Croft had shown her the whip graft
on a bench in the barn until her hands
quit shaking. In March, before the buds
moved, she took scion wood off the nine
and kept it damp and cold until May, when
the bark slipped. Every tree she set out
that spring carried wood from one of
those nine. Twenty-two years the old
trees had stood covered with nothing to
show for it. Now they had children on the
hill below them.
None of it would feed anybody soon. A
grafted pecan needs six to ten years
before it makes a crop worth hauling to a
buying station. The orchard on the east
cut belonged to Otis at twenty, not Otis
at ten.
The last week of May went dry and stayed
dry. Thirty-one days without rain, and
the ridge end of the strip sat on the
thinnest dirt on the place. She hauled
water in a two-hundred-gallon tank, two
trips a day, then three. By July eleven
of the thirty-eight had gone brown to the
graft, and there is no arguing with a
dead pecan tree. She replanted in
November and said very little about it.
In October a white county sedan came slow
along the road above the gate, slowed
further, and did not stop. Dean Whitcomb
was forty-four, the appraiser for Gilmer
County — the man whose signature decided
whether a hundred and four acres were a
farm or only dirt, and whether Corinne
kept the agricultural rate she had signed
for or owed the county the difference. He
wrote on a clipboard against the wheel
and drove on without putting the window
down.
The goats worked the north slope that
fall and went out on contract twice more.
Along the cleared fence lines the kudzu
came back every June, thinner and later
each year.
Burl came less that winter. He was
seventy-four, the cold got into his hip,
and he sat on the tailgate while she
walked the paddocks. In March he was
supposed to ride with her to the buck
sale at Ball Ground. He handed her the
folded paper instead — his notes on width
and loin and the shape of a foot, three
generations of judgment about goats in
pencil.
"You know what you're looking at," he
said. "I've told you what I see. Go tell
me what you see.".
She came back with two bucks. He studied
them a long time and never said whether
she had chosen right, which from Burl was
the answer.
That spring she opened the south slope,
sixty more pecan trees, and set the
replacements where the drought had taken
the first ones. It was the last season
she had. The county would come out to
walk the ground and decide whether any of
it had been farming.
Three seasons earlier, the only thing on
that place worth counting had been the
vines. That spring she stood at the gate
above the orchard and counted rows.
The county truck turned in at the gate on
an April morning, and Corinne heard it
before she saw it, because the cattle
guard at the road sounded like a dropped
ladder.
Dean Whitcomb changed into rubber boots
on the tailgate and said he meant to walk
the whole thing. Otis, eleven now and
taller than the top fence wire, carried
the camera bag without being asked.
They started at the road bank and worked
east. Whitcomb had a form on a clipboard
and a measuring wheel, and every so often
he stopped, wrote a figure, and took a
photograph. He asked for stocking rates
and she gave them by season, and for the
rotation: four acres at a time, moved on
the browse line. When he asked whether
any of it was written down, she came back
from the truck with a binder four seasons
thick.
That was the old job, still working for
her. Dates, head counts, rainfall, hay
prices, a contract for every place the
herd had been hired out to.
He read on the tailgate a long while,
then asked to see the trees.
The nine were up on the east shoulder,
wide-crowned now that they had light, the
wire baskets still on the trunks. Below
them the young rows followed the contour
in strips, three hundred and forty pecan
trees, not one within six years of
setting a nut worth counting. On the
north line, in two draws too steep to
fence, what was left of the kudzu still
held, and she pointed it out before he
could find it.
At the top of the slope he put the
clipboard down.
"Twenty-two years," he said. "How long
did the root take?".
"Three seasons," she said. "Four for the
rest.".
He wrote it down and said the letter
would come from the office.
It came in May and ran to three lines.
All one hundred and four acres were found
to be in bona fide agricultural use, and
the covenant remained in force. That was
the end of a clock she had been listening
to for four years. She read it twice and
went out to move fence.
The other envelope came at the end of
that summer. The county had revalued one
hundred and four acres: cleared pasture,
established orchard, working water, road
frontage. Fair market value, four hundred
sixty-two thousand eight hundred dollars.
Nobody had offered her that. It was not a
sale price, and she of all people knew
what an appraisal is and is not; under
the covenant her tax would still be
figured on farm use. It was the county's
opinion of what the ground had become —
the same ground that had stood on those
courthouse steps three times and drawn no
bid at all.
They knocked the nine trees in the last
week of October, with tarps and
fiberglass poles, and Burl Tannehill sat
at the edge of it in a lawn chair telling
Otis he was doing it wrong. The old pecan
trees had not been asked for anything in
twenty-two years. The largest gave two
hundred and thirty-one pounds. The
smallest, sixty-eight. Altogether, one
thousand three hundred and forty-one
pounds, which at the buying station was
not a living. It was a receipt with her
name on it and the word pecans above the
weight.
She laid the assessment notice on the
kitchen table that night, beside the old
ledger from Atlanta, the one she had
carried out of a job that priced other
people’s ruin. Two ways of pricing the
same ground, side by side under the same
light. She looked at them a while. Then
she made supper.
She did not call anyone. Assessments are
public, though, and Gilmer County is a
small place. The scale man at the feed
store had seen the poundage, and
somebody's wife said something in a
church basement after Wednesday supper.
By Thanksgiving every man who had laughed
on those courthouse steps had heard the
number.
Merle Yates heard it at the co-op, and he
did not say anything at all.
In December she sat down with a pencil
and worked out what it would cost to
carry the whole herd through a winter on
ground with nothing left to eat.
The browse was gone. That had been the
whole point of the goats, and it was now
the trouble with them. Kept out of the
orchard rows and off the young trees, the
herd had eleven acres of standing pasture
and a hay bill that ran past what the
lease work brought in. Burl had told her
four springs earlier that a goat is not a
mower a person can park.
She did not sell them off in a hurry.
That was not how she did anything.
She kept twenty-six head, the best of the
does and two bucks, on paper as a
breeding line and in fact because
Pepper's daughters were among them. She
kept the lease business, which by then
was the part that actually paid. The rest
of the goats she sold in ones and twos,
to people who asked questions before they
asked a price.
Merle Yates came in the second week of
December and bought nineteen.
He stood at the fence a while before he
said anything, the way he had sat at her
gate that first spring with the window
down. He did not apologize. Men like that
do not, and she would not have known
where to put it. He took his cap off,
looked up at the paddock lines, and asked
the question a man only asks after he has
made up his mind.
"If I wanted to do the back slope behind
my place," he said, "where would a man
start?".
So she told him. Nineteen head was not
enough for eight acres of vine and he
should plan on borrowing more by July.
Electric netting, four acres at a time,
moved before they get bored. And the
second season is the one that will get
you, she said, because it comes back
looking exactly like a year you wasted.
He wrote none of it down. He asked her to
say the part about the second season
again.
The goats went out of her trailer the way
they had come out of Burl's. She thought
about that on the drive back and did not
mention it to anybody.
Pepper was eleven by then, gray to the
shoulder, slow on the hill and still
first through any gate that opened. She
was not sold. On the last Sunday of the
year Corinne caught her in the lot,
unbuckled the worn strap, and lifted the
brass bell off her neck for the first
time since Burl handed it to her that
March.
She carried it up to the orchard. The
biggest of the nine, the one Otis had
named Big Tuesday when he was nine, had a
low limb that ran out over the mowed
grass at about shoulder height. She hung
the bell there and let go of it.
The wind moved it that afternoon, and it
moved on its own after that, the way
anything hung in the open will.
Otis was twelve. He stood with his hands
in his jacket pockets and listened a long
while.
"Now you can find the middle of it in the
dark," he said.
Four springs before, the county had
offered one hundred and four acres three
times and taken no bid, because everyone
who looked saw a hillside that had quit
being land and turned into weather. It
was never dead ground. It was covered
ground. That is a different word, and it
took a woman with a ledger, eighty-three
goats, and four growing seasons to say
the difference out loud.
The ninety-one thousand four hundred
dollars was not the expensive part. The
expensive part was standing at a fence
for four seasons while men she had to see
at the feed store every week made a joke
out of her, and going out the next
morning to move the netting anyway.
People come up the drive now and ask what
she would take for the place. She tells
them it is not for sale, and offers them
coffee, and most stay long enough to walk
the rows.
The young trees are not worth anything
yet. Three hundred and forty of them, set
in strips down a slope that used to be
one color, and none will carry a real
crop before Otis is old enough to vote.
She knew that when she planted them.
The bell is still on the limb. On a still
morning it does not carry as far as the
house. On a windy one it carries all the
way to the road.
Send this story to someone who is holding
on to a thing that everybody has told
them to let go of. And down in the
comments, tell us about the place where
you saw nothing but weeds, and the person
who saw something worth keeping.